Guide to the Incunabula Collection at Stanford University, 1467-1500
Department of Special Collections
- Persius. Auli Flacci Persii poetae Satyraru[m] opus.[Venice]: Per me magistru[m] Renaldu[m] de Nouimagio Theutonicu[m] Venetiis impressum, anno M.CCCC.LXXXII. me[n]sis Dece[m]bris die XXIIII [24 Dec. 1482], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1482 .P38 f; [44] p.; 31 cm.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: capitals added in red or black ink; initial strokes and underscoring in black. Extensive ms. marginalia. Imperfect: lacks a1 (blank); leaves trimmed, with loss of marginalia. Binding: quarter pink sheepskin, red marbled boards.
- Eusebius, of Caesarea, Bishop of Caesarea, ca. 260-ca. 340. Eusebii Caesariensis Episcopi Chronicon, id est temporum breuiarium incipit foeliciter / quem Hieronymus praesbiter diuino eius ingenio Latinum facere curauit et usque in Valente[m] C[a]esarem Romano adiecit eloquio; que[m] et Prosper deinde Mathe[us] Palmeri[us] qui ea qu[a]e co[n]secuta su[n]t adiicere curauere eide[m] postpositi subsequunt[ur].[Venice: Erhard Ratdolt, 13 Sept. 1483], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1483 .E89; [364] p.; 23 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 287 (IA.20527). Goff (rev.), E-117. GW 9433. Hain-Copinger, 6717. ISTC, ie00117000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Foliation added in ink; pagination in pencil. Imperfect: lacks final blank (x10). Binding: limp vellum, with fore-edge flap and ties. In box with spine title: Eusebius Chronikon. Provenance: [W?] Blair (signature); Cancz. Attilij Lucini [I.V.D.?] (inscription); ms. marginalia.
- Filelfo, Francesco, 1398-1481. Francisci Philelfi ad Thomam Thebaldum Mediolanense conuiuium primum- [secundum].[Milan: Simon Magniagus, 1483-1484], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1483 .F54; [192] p. (last p. blank); 21 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., VI, p. 760 (IA.26605). Goff (rev.), P-605. Hain-Copinger, 12956. ISTC, ip00605000. Polain 4653. Proctor 7268.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Variant: text on b3r, lines 25-27 matches BM IA.26605 (earlier uncorrected state?). Imperfect: lacks quire A (p.[1]-[8]), containing errata and letter of Marlianus. Cf. BM 15th cent., V, p. 760. Foliation ([1]-92) added in ink; extensive ms. marginalia; ms. writing on tail. Binding: modern paper; in box, with spine label: Mediolanensia.
- Pliny, the Younger. Caii Plinii secundi nouocomensis oratoris facundissimi epistolarum liber primus incipit.[Treviso]: Impressum quidem est hoc opus Taruisii per Magistru[m] Ioannem Vercellium, anno salutis M.cccclxxxiii [1483], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1483 .P49; [184] p.; 21 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., VI, p. 896 (IA.28433). Goff (rev.), P-808. Hain-Copinger, 13113. ISTC, ip00808000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Provenance: hand-painted coat of arms on a2: 3 cinquefoils and chevron in gold on blue ground, with motto: Virtus et honor; extensive ms. marginalia, fists and marginal drawings in several hands. Rubrication: 2 capitals on leaf a2 supplied in gold, with blue, purple and green background; other capitals added in red or blue ink; Greek supplied only on a2. Foliation added in ink. Imperfect: lacks a1 (blank). Binding: full calf, with decorative geometric border. Binder's title: Plinii Epistolae. Taruisii 1483.
- Premonstratensians. Incipit Ordinarius Premonstratensis: de reuerentia circa altare.[Lbeck: Matthus Brandis, not after 1483], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1483 .P74 f; [112] p. (last 10 p. blank); 30 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 555 (IB.9935). Goff (rev.), 0-86. Hain 12060. ISTC (RLIN), io00086000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Imperfect: lacks final 2 blank leaves. Binding: vellum leaf from antiphonal; title in ms. on spine; in case. Binder's title: Ordinarius Praemonstratensis. Provenance: ms. addition on 1st blank leaf at end, beginning: Incipit ordinarium horarum Beatae Mariae Virginis secundum usum Praemonstratensis Ordinis.
- Petrus, de Abano, 1250-ca. 1315. Conciliator differentiaru[m] philosophoru[m] [et] precipue medicoru[m]. Impressum Venetiijs: Ioha[n]nis Herbort de Selge[n]stat, a[n]no v[?] 1483. nonis Februis [5 February 1483], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1483 .P388 f; [568] p.; 33 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 303 (IB.21557). Goff (rev.), P-433. Hain-Copinger 6. ISTC (RLIN), ip00433000. Polain 3072."Sequitur tabula": 2g4r-2g5v.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: untouched. Imperfect: lacks a1 (blank). Binding: boards covered with early printed leaf with Latin text and musical notation, rubricated. Title label on spine: Petrus de Abano; shelf tag, numbered 3, on lower spine; in case with title: Conciliator. Provenance: Lib. Antiquaria Bourlot fond. 1848 Torino (Italia) (label); ms. marginalia (some trimmed); 11 blank leaves in front, lettered A-L, and 10 blank leaves at end, lettered M-X, with ms. notations.
- Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321. Comento di Christophoro Landino fiorentino sopra La comedia di Danthe Alighieri poeta fiorentino. Impresso in Vinegia: Per Octauiano Scoto da Monza, adi 23 di Marzo 1484., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1484 .D36 f; [540] p. (first and last p. blank); 33 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 279 (IB.21213). Goff (rev.), D-30. GW 7967. Hain-Copinger, 5947. ISTC, id00030000. Mambelli, G. Ed. Dantesche, 11.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: on b1r, woodcut initial colored in gilt and green; banner enclosing caption title, Inferno, and coat of arms at bottom of page, both in gilt and colors. Foliation supplied in ms. Binding: half green leather, green marbled boards, gilt spine. Binder's title: Dante col comento del Landino. Provenance: Giorgio Fanan (bookplate); D. Antonio Dragoni (signature and booklabel); scant ms. marginalia, some cropped.
- Felicianus. Short Title: De divina praedestinatione Full title: Incipit tractatus Fratris Feliciani Ordinis Predicato[rum] doctoris eximij De diuina predestinatione intitulatus. Part title: De retentione decimarum Nota 25 privilegia clericorum. 1485. Tractatus de decimis. 1485. Impressum Me[m]mingen: P[er] Albertu[m] Ku[n]ne, [ca. 1485], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1485 .F35; [40] p.; 20 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent.,cII, p. 604 (IA. 11052). GW 9732. Goff (rev.), F-55. Hain 6952. ISTC (RLIN), if00055000. Proctor 2782.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Binding: blind ruled black calf. Provenance: Johannes Sois[?] (signature).
- Leo I, Pope, d. 461. Sermoni di beato Leone papa di lingua latina in toscana ... tradocti. Prohemio di Philippo di Bartholomeo Corsini cittadino fiorentino sopra de Sermoni di beato Leone papa Impresso in Firenze: [Antonio di Bartolommeo Miscomini], a di xxi di maggio 1485., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1485 .L463; [4], CLXVIII, [2] leaves (the last leaf blank): 29 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., VI, p. 638 (IB.27173). Goff (rev.), L-136. Hain-Copinger 10016. ISTC (RLIN), il00136000. Errors in printed foliation: leaf 13 blank; leaf 23 numbered 24; leaf 166 numbered 169.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): untouched; foliation (with errors) added in ink, in Arabic numerals. Binder: K.A. 1905 [i.e. Katherine Adams] (stamped on lower turn-in). Binding: full pigskin; turn-ins; all edges gilt. Binder's title: Sermoni di papa S. Leone. Provenance: C.H. St. John Hornby (bookplate label); Philip C. Duschnes (bookseller's label).
- Attavanti, Paolo, d. 1499. Egregij theologie professoris magistri Pauli Flore[n]tini diui Ordinis Sancti Spirit[us] de Roma totius canonici juris breuiarium: primo decretoru[m] secundo decretaliu[m] perutile ad colendissimu[m] Patrem [et] Dominu[m] Innocentiu[m] ... feliciter jncipit. Impressu[m] Me[m]ming[en]: Per Albertum Ku[n]ne d[e] Duderstat, anno salutis 1486., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1486 .A88; [4], CXXIX, [1] (blank) leaves: port.; 29 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 604 (IB.11042). Goff (rev.), P-180. Hain 7161. ISTC, ip00180000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): untouched. Binding: tooled leather over boards; remains of 2 fore-edge clasps. Provenance: monastic inscription [Bozen?] on 1st leaf, repeated on LIX and lower paste- down; Eduardo J. Bullrich (booklabel). Imperfect: half of final blank torn off.
- Bartholomaeus, de Chaimis. Incipit interrogatorium siue confessionale / per venerabilem Fratrem Bartholomeum de Chaimis de Mediolano ordinis mino[rum] ... Impressu[m] Venetijs: Per Reynaldu[m] de Nouimagio Teoteutonicu[m], anno salutis 1486 adi 28 Septembris., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1486 .B37; [112] p. (1st 2 p. and last p. blank); 20 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 258 (IA.20688) GW 6549. Goff (rev.), B-162. Hain-Copinger (Add.), 2488*. ISTC (RLIN), ib00162000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): untouched. Imperfect: lacks a1 (blank). Binding: brown morocco, blind stamped on upper and lower covers, panelled spine; gilt decorated turn-ins, marbled end-papers, all edges gilt. Binder's title: Interrogatorium sive confessionale. Provenance: A.L.S. (booklabel); scant ms. marginalia. Leaves numbered 68-122 in ms.
- Boethius, d. 524. Auitij Maulij Torquati Seuerini Boetij ordinarij patricij viri exconsulis De consolatione ph[ilosoph]ie liber primus incipit. Auitii Maulii Torquati Severini Boetii ordinarii patricii viri exconsulis De consolatione philosophie liber primus incipit[Nuremberg]: Anthonij Kobergers ciuis inclyte Nure[m]bergensiu[m] vrbis industria fabrefactus ..., anno a Natiuitate [Christ]i millesimo cccclxxxvj. in vigilia Sancti Iohannis Baptiste [23 June 1486], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1486 .B64 f; [148] p.; 32 cm.
  Includes index (pi2-pi5), printed in 2 columns.
  References: Refs.BM 15th cent., II, p. 430 (IB.7353). Goff (rev.), B-781. GW 4537. Hain-Copinger 3378. ISTC (RLIN), ib00781000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initials, initial strokes, and paragraph marks in red. Imperfect: lacks pi1, i9 and i10 (blanks). Binding: half blind-stamped leather, wooden boards, modern metal clasp. Provenance: Ewald Flgel Library (booklabel and ink-stamp); Oswald Weigel Antiquariat Auctions-Institut, Leipzig ... (ink- stamp); Ad bibliothecam Mon[aste?]rii S. Mich. Arch. O.S.B. Bambergae (inscription); ms. marginalia; signature (?) below colophon. With: Seneca, Lucius Annaeus. Senece Omnia opere. Venetiis impressa: Per Bernardinu[m] de Coris de Cremona, 1492 die ultima Octobris [31 October 1492]
- Seneca, Lucius Annaeus, ca. 4 B.C.-65 A.D. Senece Omnia opera. Venetiis impressa: Per Bernardinu[m] de Coris de Cremona, 1492 die ultima Octobris [31 October 1492], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1486 .B64 f; [2], ccviii leaves; 32 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent, V, p. 466 (IB.23442). Goff (rev.), S-371. Hain-Copinger 14594. ISTC (RLIN), is00371000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initials and paragraph marks in red. Binding: half blind-stamped leather, wooden boards, modern metal clasp. Provenance: Ewald Flgel Library (booklabel and ink- stamp); Oswald Weigel Antiquariat Auctions-Institut, Leipzig ... (ink-stamp). With: Boethius. [De consolatione philosophiae] Autij Maulij Torquati Seuerini Boetij ordinarij patricij viri exconsulis De consolatione philsophiae liber primus incipit. [Nuremberg]: Anthonij Kobergers ciuis inclyte Nure[m]bergensiu[m] vrbis indutria fabrefactus ..., anno a Natiuitate [Christ]i millesimo cccclxxxvj. in vigilia Sancti Iohannes Baptiste [23 June 1486]
- Breydenbach, Bernhard von, d. 1497. Prefatio in opus transmarine peregrinationis ad venerandu[m] et gloriosum sepulcru[m] Dominicu[m] in Iherusale[m] ... Prefatio in opus transmarine peregrinationis ad venerandum et gloriosum sepulcrum Dominicum in Iherusalem ... Impressum in ciuitate Moguntina: P[er] Erhardu[m] Rewich de Traiecto Inferiori, anno salutis 1486 die xj Februarij., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1486 .B73 f; [296] p. (1st p. and last 2 p. blank): ill.; 30 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., I, p. 43 (IB.331). Goff (rev.), B-1189. GW 5075. Hain-Copinger 3956. ISTC (RLIN), ib01189000. Pellechet 2979.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Arrangement: follows Pellechet 2979, except gathering 22 is bound in gathering 23, the 1st 4 leaves of which are: Pellechet's Fnc. 133, Fnc. 131-132 [= BM's 146,147], and a leaf headed: Sequu[n]tur quedam co[m]munia vocabula de ydiomate Sarracenico in Latinum translata. Gatherings of 2 at beginning are, in order, maps of: Venice, Parenzo, Corfu, Modon, Candia, and Rhodes. Rubrication: large initials and floral borders on leaves 8r and 100v in red, blue, green and gold; other initials in red, blue and red and blue; initial strokes in gold. Imperfect: last (blank) leaf lacking. Binding: blind-stamped leather; panelled spine; ms. labels on paper on spine and lower cover. Provenance: [Deusdtsoj?] Jesu e Maria P.B.M. Zdak[a?] (inscription); Bibliotheca Arahoviensis (inscription and ink-stamp); ms. marginalia, underscoring, Arabic leaf nos. at beginning, inscription on end-paper of lower cover.
- Pergola, Paolo della, d. 1455. Compendium peclarum ad introductio[n]em iuuenum in facultate logice per clarum artium doctorem ac theologie professorem magistrum Paulum Pergulensem nuperrime compilatum quam faustissime incipit. Impressum Venetiis: Per Baptistam de Tortis, M.cccc.lxxxvi die xiii Septe[m]bris [13 Sept. 1486], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1486 .P35; [100] p.: diagrams; 20 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 324 (IA.21379). Goff (rev.), P-192. Hain 12623. ISTC, ip00192000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: woodcut initials and diagram colored in red, initial strokes added, p. [1]-[5] only. Binding error: d3.6 bound between d4.5. Binder [?]: CP, 25-10-79 (pencilled on lower paste-down). Binding: full vellum, with fold-over fore- edges; in case. Title on cover: Paulus Pergulensis. Compendium logices. Venetiis. B. de Tortis. 1486. Provenance: George Dunn of Woolley Hall (booklabel); scant ms. marginalia.
- Saucius, Cristophorus. Oratio metrica habita i[n] p[ri]ncipio studii Bononiensis. Short title: Carmina.[Leipzig: Printer of Capotius (Martin Landsberg?), between 1486 and 1489], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1486 .S28; [12] p. (last p. blank); 19 cm.
  References: Goff (rev.), S-165. Hain 14330. ISTC, is00165000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Binding: quarter buff cloth, brown boards; in portfolio. Provenance: R. Hildebrand (signature); Hildebrand Library (ink-stamp).
- Beroaldo, Filippo, 1453-1505. Ad magnificum Minum Roscium Philippi Beroaldi Bononiensis Co[m]mentarii in Propertium. Impressi uero Bononiae: In co[m]mune a Benedicto Hectoris librario et Platone de Benedictis impressore ..., anno 1487., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1487 .B478 f; [208] p. (1st 2 p. and last p. blank); 30 cm.
  Includes: Hieronymi Salii Fauentini In inuidum carmen (s4r).
  References: BM 15th cent., VI, p. 822 (IB.28863). Goff (rev.), P-1017. Hain-Copinger-Reichling, 13406. ISTC (RLIN), ip01017000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Imperfect: 1st blank leaf lacking. Binding: grey boards, paper title label on upper cover; call number on spine. Provenance: ms. marginalia and underscoring.
- Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321. Comento di Christophforo Landino fiorentino sopra la Comedia di Danthe Alighieri poeta fiorentino. Impresso in Bressa: Per Boninum de Boninis di Raguxi, a di ultimo di Mazo .M.CCCC.LXXXVII [31 May 1487], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1487 .D36 f; [620] p. (the last [2] p. blank): ill. (woodcuts); 34 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., VII, p. 971 (IB.31103). Copinger 5943. GW 7968. Goff D-31. ISTC (RLIN), id00031000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: untouched. Provenance: Giorgio Fanan (bookplate). Imperfect: wanting L6 (blank).
- Ars moriendi (Version beginning: Cum de praesentis exilii miseria mortis transitus). Italian. Short title: Questa operecta tracta dellarte del be[n] morire cioe i[n] gratia didio.[Florence: Francesco di Dino, 7 Feb. 1487, i.e. 1488], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1488 .A77; [64] p.; 19 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., VI, p. 633 (IA.27693). Goff (rev.), A-1107. GW 2625. Hain-Copinger 4400. ISTC, ia01107000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): variants: BM and GW transcribe title with "ben", "in"; BM colophon reads correctly "Maria". Binding error: a8 and b1 bound following t.p., a1. Binding: full vellum; rubricated ms. guards on some quires. Binder's title: Capranica. Firenze, Franc. de Dino 1487.
- Peter Lombard, Bishop of Paris, ca. 1100-1160. Textus sentenciaru[m] cum Conclusionibus ac titulis questionu[m] S. Thome articulisq[ue] Parisien. et in quibus magister communiter non tenetur.[Basel]: Impensis ... Nicolai Keslers ciuis Basileen[sis] ..., [22 September 1488]., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1488 .P382 f; [562] p. (the last 2 p. blank); 32 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., III, p. 766 (IB.37609). Hain-Copinger 10195. Goff (rev.), P-491. ISTC (RLIN), ip00491000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initial strokes and underscoring in red, to d4r. Imperfect: t6 (blank) mostly cut away. Binding: quarter blind-tooled deerskin, wooden boards, remains of clasps. On spine: Pet. Lombar. Lib. IIII Sentent. Basil. 1488. Nic. Kesler. Provenance: Conventus S. Petri (inscription); Bundesdenkmalamt (ink-stamp); Kleins in the pines (bookplate). Extensive ms. marginalia throughout.
- Abu Ma`shar, d. 886 Authorized title: Selections. Latin Title: Albumasar De magnis coniunctionibus: annorum reuolutionibus ac eorum profectionibus, octo continens tractatus. Short title: Albumasar.[Augsburg]: Erhardiq[ue] Ratdolt viri solertis ..., qua nup[er] Venetijs, nunc Auguste Vindelico[rum] excellit no[m]i[n]atissim[us], pridie Kal[endas] Aprilis [31 Mar.], 1489., Call No. Barchas Collection KA1489 .A28; [236] p.: ill., diagrs. (woodcuts); 22 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 383 (IA.6689). GW 836. Goff (rev.) A-360. Hain-Copinger, 611*. ISTC, ia00360000. Stillwell, M.B. Science, 9.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (BARCH): Blank spaces for woodcut ill. on M8v and N4r. Binding: full calf, gilt spine. Binder's title: Albumasar. Provenance: Richard Biddulph Martin (booklabel). With: Abu Ma`shar. [Al-Mudkhal al-kabir ila `ilm ahkam al-nujum. Latin] Introductorium in astronomia[m] Albumasaris Abalachi octo continens libros partiales. [Augsburg]: Erhardi Ratdolt ..., qua nuper Venetijs nunc Auguste Vindelico[rum] excellit no[m]i[n]atissimus, 7 Idus Februarij [7 Feb.] 1489.
- Abu Ma`shar, d. 886 Introductorium in astronomia[m] Albumasaris Abalachi octo continens libros partiales.[Augsburg]: Erhardi Ratdolt ... qua nuper Venetijs nunc Auguste Vindelico[rum] excellit no[m]i[n]atissimus, 7 Idus Februarij [7 Feb.] 1489., Call No. Barchas Collection KA1489 .A28; [140] p.: ill., diagrs. (woodcuts); 22 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 382 (IA.6683). GW 840. Goff (rev.) A-359. Hain-Copinger, 612*. ISTC, ia00359000. Stillwell, M.B. Science, 9.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (BARCH): Binding: full calf, gilt spine. Binder's title: Albumasar. Provenance: Richard Biddulph Martin (booklabel). With: Abu Ma`shar. [Selections. Latin] Albumasar De magnis coniunctionibus. [Augsburg]: Erhardiq[ue] Ratdolt viri solertis ..., qua nup[er] Venetijs, nunc Auguste Vindelico[rum] excellit no[m]i[n]atissim[us], pridie Kal[endis] Aprilis [31 Mar.] 1489.
- Eschuid, Joannes, fl. 1350. Summa astrologiae iudicialis de accidentibus mundi quae anglicana uulgo nuncupatur Ioannis Eshcuidi [sic] niri [i.e. uiri] anglici peritissimi scie[n]tiae astrologiae foelici sidere inchoat. Short title: Summa astrologiae. Impressione completum est Venetiis: Iohannis Lucilii Sanctiter, ... impensis ... Fra[n]cisci Bolani ..., 1489 nonis Iulii [7th July], Call No. Barchas Collection KA1489 .E8 f; [2], 306 [i.e. 218], [1] leaves: ill., map; 31 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 462 (IB.23335). Goff (rev.) E-109. GW 9392. Hain 6685*. ISTC, ie00109000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (BARCH): Binding: quarter white cloth, brown boards. Binder's title: Eschcudii J. Summa astrologiae. Provenance: Heinrich Trnker (ink-stamp).
- Ficino, Marsilio, 1433-1499. De triplici vita Florentiae: Impressit ex archetypo Antonius Mischominus, anno salutis 1489 tertio Nonas Decembr. [3 Dec.], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1489 .F49; [180] p. (last p. blank); 26 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., VI, p. 639 (IB.27180). Goff (rev.), F-158. GW 9882. Hain-Copinger, 7065. ISTC (RLIN), if00158000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Untouched. Imperfect: last three leaves damaged, partly mended, with partial loss of text. Binding: brown boards. Provenance: Ewald Flgel (signature); ms. marginalia.
- Filelfo, Giovanni Mario, 1426-1480. Novum epistolarium Title: Epistolare Marii Philelfi. Basileae: Per Magistru[m] Ioannem De Amerbach summa lucubratione impressum, anno [1489], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1489 .F55; [320] p. (the last 2 p. blank); 22 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., III, p. 752 (IA.37326). Goff (rev.), P-619. Hain-Copinger 12974*. ISTC (RLIN), ia00619000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: ruled in red, some underscoring and initial strokes. Imperfect: lacks final blank leaf (u8) called for by BM. Binding error: u1,u2 bound between u6 and u7. Binding: half vellum paper, brown marbled boards; title label on spine. Binder's title: Epistolare Marii Philelfi. Provenance: General Theological Seminary Library, New York (booklabel).
- Versor, Johannes, d. ca. 1485. Questiones M[a]g[ist]ri Ioha[n]nis Versoris super libros De celo [et] mu[n]do cu[m] textu Arestotelis.[Cologne: Heinrich Quentell], anno incarnat[i]o[n]is D[omi]nice 1489 penultimo die Maij [30 May], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1489 .V47 f; [344] p.; 30 cm.
  References: Goff (rev.), V-253. Hain-Copinger, 16047. ISTC (RLIN), iv00253000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Imperfect: consists only of the 1st part, the commentary on De caelo and De mundo ([1], 52, [1] leaves); all after leaf [54] lacking. Rubrication: initials, initial strokes, paragraph marks and underscoring in red. Binding: vellum leaf with Biblical text. Provenance: Pierre Duhem (booklabel); Stewart M. Marshall and Ellen E.M. Marshall (ink-stamp); VF (ink-stamp); ms. marginalia and underscoring.
- Catholic Church. Cancellaria Apostolica. Taxe Cancellarie Apostolice sequunt[ur] et primo de gratijs expectatiuis.[Rome: s.n., ca. 1490?], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1490 .C38; [36] p. (last p. blank); 19 cm.
  References: Hain 15352.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Binding: modern vellum, with 18 blank leaves bound at end; in case. Spine title: Taxae Cancellariae apostolicae (c. 1490).
- Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321. Convivio di Dante Alighieri Fiorentino. Impresso in Firenze: Per Ser Francesco Bonaccorsi, nel anno mille quattrocento nouanta adi xx di septembre [20 Sept. 1490], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1490 .D37; [180] p. (last p. blank); 21 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., VI, p. 673 (IA.27611). GW 7973. Goff (rev), D-36. Hain-Copinger, 5954. ISTC (RLIN), id00036000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Binding: vellum. Provenance: Giorgio Fanan (bookplate).
- Duns Scotus, John, ca. 1266-1308. Primus Sententiarum doctoris subtilis Scoti.[Venice: Bernardinus Rizus, 17 July 1490], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1490 .D78; 184 [i.e. 185], [l] (blank) leaves; 27 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 401 (IB.22635). Goff (rev.), D-382. GW 9076. Hain 6419. ISTC, id00382000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Imperfect: lacks t.p. (a1) and final blank (z10); title from BM 15th cent.; worming affects text, a2-3. Binding: brown pigskin. On spine: Bernardini de Nouaria. Venetiis, 1490. Provenance: Paul Louis Feiss (bookplate).
- Proba, 4th cent. Virgiliocentones Veteris et Noui Testamenti.[Leipzig: Printer of Capotius (Martin Landsberg?), ca. 1490], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1490 .P76; [40] p. (last p. blank); 19 cm.